A Guide to the Philip Alexander Bruce Papers 1871-1933
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Philip Alexander Bruce 1871-1933
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2889
The Philip Alexander Bruce Collection, 1871-1933, comprises 3.5 linear feet of his correspondence and manuscripts.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Bruce papers were given to Alderman Libary by his daughter, Mrs. Archibald B. Shepperson, in 1948.
Biographical/Historical Information
Philip A. Bruce (1856-1933) was a historian, essayist, and poet of Scotch descent. The son of Charles and Sarah Seddon Bruce, Philip spent his youth at Staunton Hall Plantation in Charlotte County, Virginia. Deeply influenced by the social and cultural life of the plantation, Bruce received a good education from various tutors. Later, he attended Norwood Academy; and then the University of Virginia from 1873 to 1875. He obtained a Bachelor of Law degree from Harvard in 1879.
Bruce's career was varied and colorful. His first position as editorial writer for The Richmond Times brought him recognition as a promising writer. As corresponding secretary of the Virginia Historical Society, Bruce played a major role editing its quarterly publication. Bruce never taught, but devoted his full creative energies to writing. In 1896 his major work The Economic History of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century appeared. Bruce spent time in England to research colonial Virginia records. He published a social and institutional history of Virginia and a History of the University of Virginia(5 vols.) in 1921. For additional biographical information, see Darrett B. Rutman, "Philip Alexander Bruce: A Divided Mind of the South" Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, LXVIII (Oct. 1960), pp. 387-408.
Scope and Content Information
The Bruce papers include correspondence between Bruce and various persons concerning his publications, business and personal matters, as well as family papers. Prominent correspondents include Thomas Seddon Bruce, William Cabell Bruce, Armistead Gordon, Mr. and Mrs. John Kelsall, Frederick Viaux, and Gerald Smythe. The remainder of the collection contains miscellaneous printed materials and research notes. There are newspaper clippings, publication agreements, leases, poems, typescripts of published works, and a few photos of Bruce. There are five scrapbooks (1888-1933) of newspaper clippings. Manuscript notebooks include: "Intimate Sidelights on Belligerent England," "Thomas Jefferson as Secretary of State," and "Edgar Allan Poe." Box 10 contains the Stony Point Plantation papers. Bruce inherited the plantation when his mother died in 1907. The papers include correspondence on business matters relating to care and management of the farm. There are accounts, deeds, sale agreements, and plats showing the extent of the land holdings.
This collection of Bruce papers should be used in conjunction with collection 2889-a which contains an autobiographical sketch of Bruce, typed extracts from the Bruce family Bibles, copies of letters of James Coles Bruce and Henry Bruce and various other materials.
Arrangement
The papers were originally filed by the Library in loose chronological order. They have now been arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent, and there are folders containing miscellaneous letters A to Z. These materials fill the first five boxes. Boxes 6 to 9 contain miscellaneous printed materials and research notes, typescripts of poems, sonnets, and published articles, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, and manuscript notebooks. Box 10 contains the Stony Point Plantation papers organized mainly by correspondents.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Edwin Alderman to P. A. Bruce 1917-1929 (Box 1)
  - Joseph R. Anderson to Mrs. Bruce 1923 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Wm. B. Baldwin to Mrs. Bruce 1915-1931 (Box 1)
  - Baylor Family to Mrs. Bruce 1915, 1933 (Box 1)
  - J. P. Bell Co. to P. A. Bruce 1927, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Landon C. Bell [Author] to P. A. Bruce 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Olaf Bjorkman to P. A. Bruce 1921, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. and Mrs. Charles Bruce to their son P. A. Bruce 1871-1875 (Box 1)
  - Charles Norelle Bruce to P. A. Bruce 1923-1925 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. and Mrs. Malcolm Bruce to P. A. Bruce 1925-1927 (Box 1)
  - P. A. Bruce to Mrs. and Mrs. Paul Barringer 1916 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Mrs. and Mrs. Bruce 1896-1921 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. and Mrs. Bruce to Mr. and Mrs. Charles Bruce 1878-1901 (Box 1)
  - Phillippa Bruce, Correspondence to and from various writers 1933 and n.d. (Box 1)
  - Mrs. and Mrs. Thomas Seddon Bruce to Mrs. and Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1915, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Seddon Bruce to P. A. Bruce 1901-1939
  - Mr. and Mrs. Cabell Bruce to Mr. and Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1889-1921 (Box 1)
  - Wm. Cabell Bruce Family to Mr. and Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1920-1933 (Box 1)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Wm. Cabell Bruce to Mr. and Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1922-1936 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. W. Case [English] to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1915-1927 (Box 1)
  - R. G. Chandler to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1923-1929 (Box 1)
  - John A. Chaloner to P. A. Bruce 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Harry Clemons to P. A. Bruce 1928, 1930 (Box 1)
  - W. Couch to P. A. Bruce 1929 (Box 1)
  - Virginius Dabney to P. A. Bruce 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - A. K. Davis to P. A. Bruce 1926 (Box 2)
  - Lambert Davis to P. A. Bruce 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - E. Drummond [English] to P. A. Bruce 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - H. J. Eckenrode to P. A. Bruce 1927-1931 (Box 2)
  - J. D. Eggleston to P. A. Bruce 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - Mr. and Mrs. G. Briscoe Eyre to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1914-1922 (Box 2)
  - George Fawcett to P. A. Bruce 1925-1928 (Box 2)
  - Worthington C. Ford to P. A. Bruce 1921, 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - J. E. Gaines to P. A. Bruce 1927-1931 (Box 2)
  - Wilson Gee to P. A. Bruce 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - Armistead C. Gordon to P. A. Bruce 1910-1933 (Box 2)
    (3 folders)
  - Raymond Gorges to P. A. Bruce 1929, 1931 (Box 2)
  - R. M. Graham [English] to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1915-1922 (Box 2)
  - Fairfax Harrison to P. A. Bruce 1916-1933 (Box 3)
  - Archibald Henderson to P. A. Bruce 1917-1932 (Box 3)
  - Arthur Humphreys to P. A. Bruce 1924-1929 (Box 3)
  - Allen Johnson [editor D.A.B.] to P. A. Bruce 1926-1927 (Box 3)
  - Mrs. John Kelsall to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1914-1936 (Box 3)
  - John Kelsall to P. A. Bruce 1914-1927 (Box 3)
  - John Kelsall to P. A. Bruce 1914-1927 (Box 3)
  - Gordon McCabe to P. A. Bruce 1911-1918 (Box 3)
  - George McIntosh to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1899-1929 (Box 3)
  - John C. Metcalf to P. A. Bruce 1921-1930 (Box 3)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Nelson Page to P. A. Bruce 1921-1930 (Box 3)
  - Walter H. Page to P. A. Bruce 1913 (Box 3)
  - John S. Patton to P. A. Bruce 1920-1929 (Box 3)
  - Seldon Piercy to P. A. Bruce 1924 (Box 3)
  - Governor J. G. Pollard to P. A. Bruce 1930-1932 (Box 3)
  - James Putman to P. A. Bruce 1935 (Box 3)
  - Putnam's Sons to P. A. Bruce 1899, 1910 (Box 3)
  - O. M. Reynolds to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1924, 1934, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Jack Ross to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1923-1931 (Box 3)
  - Dunbar Rowland [Mississippi State historian] to P. A. Bruce 1927-1933 (Box 3)
  - Mary E. Rowland to P. A. Bruce 1925-1930 (Box 3)
  - Louise Savage to A. B. Shepperson 1947 (Box 3)
  - Harold R. Shurtleff to P. A. Bruce 1932 (Box 3)
  - Tunstall Smith to P. A. Bruce 1919-1926 (Box 3)
  - Gerald Smythe to P. A. Bruce 1916-1929 (Box 4)
    (2 folders)
  - Wm. G. Stanard to P. A. Bruce 1921-1932 (Box 4)
  - E. G. Swem [Librarian W and M] to P. A. Bruce 1926-1927 (Box 4)
  - Prince Pierre Troubetzkoy to P. A. Bruce 1917, 1922, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Lyon G. Tyler to P. A. Bruce 1911-1932 (Box 4)
  - Frederick H. Viaux to P. A. Bruce 1923-1933 (Box 4)
  - J. H. Whitty to P. A. Bruce 1918-1928 (Box 4)
  - James Southall Wilson to P. A. Bruce 1925-1930 (Box 4)
  - Woodrow Wilson to P. A. Bruce 1911-1912 (Box 4)
  - Jennings C. Wise to P. A. Bruce 1915-1930 (Box 4)
  - George Evelyn Wood to Mrs. P. A. Bruce 1916-1933 (Box 4)
  - Bessie Zeban to P. A. Bruce 1929-1930 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, A-Z n.d. (Box 5)
    (4 folders)
  - Miscellaneous notations concerning Bruce papers n.d. (Box 5)
  - Telegrams on Death of Dr. Bruce 1933 (Box 5)
  - Publications on death of Dr. Bruce 1933 (Box 5)
  - Publications Agreements 1895-1929 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Papers 1902-1932 (Box 5)
  - Leases 1918 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings 1923-1925 (Box 5)
  - Schoolboy compositions, Norwood School, Virginia 1872 (Box 6)
  - Addresses: "Social Life of Virginia" - "George Eliot" 1909 and n.d. (Box 6)
  - Book Reviews by P. A. Bruce 1912, 1925 (Box 6)
  - Address by Mrs. Bruce at Class Reunion "VMI in 1873" 1923 (Box 6)
  - Research concerning Maltravers Grant 1926 (Box 6)
  - Bookplate of P. A. Bruce n.d. (Box 6)
  - Bruce's outlines for account of Colonial Virginia n.d. (Box 6)
  - Poem: "In Sussex, England" 1915 (Box 6)
  - Poem: "The Bells of Ashtead" 1915 (Box 6)
  - Poem: "Cape Henry" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Poem: "Ballad of London Wind" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Sonnets and Poems: "Pocahontas" and others n.d. (Box 6)
  - Various printed articles: "Negro Problem" - "Poe at U. Va." - "England During War" 1911, 1915 (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Va. on the Defensive" 1925 (Box 6)
  - "Cub Creek Church" by Elizabeth V. Gaines 1929 Jul 4 (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Letters to Mrs. Elizabeth Bruce from Raymond Gorges" 1933-1934 (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Negro Migration Northward" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Damon and Pythias" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Aspects of Southern Development" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Typescript: "Birds of English Water-Meadows" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Essay: Typescript "Florence" n.d. (Box 6)
  - Photos of Bruce n.d. (Box 6)
  - Various invitations n.d. (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook: Editorials while Chief Editorial writer of Richmond Times 1888-1891 and miscellaneous 1888-1926 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook: Newspaper clippings 1896-1910 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook: Newspaper clippings, Reviews, etc. 1899-1911 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook: Newspaper Clippings 1902-1933 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook: Newspaper Clippings 1911-1917 (Box 8)
  - Two Memorandum Books 1919-1920 and n.d. (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook: Reviews of History of U. Va. 1921-1923 (Box 8)
- Bound Volumes
  - Manuscript: "Intimate Sidelights on Belligerent England" 1915 (Box 9)
  - Typescript: "Thomas Jefferson as Secretary of State" 1925 (Box 9)
  - Manuscript: "Edgar Allen Poe: An Interpretation" n.d. (Box 9)
  - Notebooks, Drafts of Poe Ms n.d. (Box 9)
- Stony Point Plantation
  - J. E. Baldwin to P. A. Bruce re Business Affairs 1920-1927 (Box 10)
  - Philip A. Bruce, Statement concerning plantation 1908-1927 (Box 10)
  - W. Claybrook to P. A. Bruce re land sale 1921-1923 (Box 10)
  - Marcellus French to P. A. Bruce re surveying 1911-1917 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and Agreements between J. E. Gaines and P. A. Bruce 1913-1919 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence of J. E. Gaines to P. A. Bruce 1920-1926 (Box 10)
  - R. F. Gilliand to P. A. Bruce re business matters 1922-1925 (Box 10)
  - H. J. Hamlett to Bruce re business matters 1916-1926 (Box 10)
  - Hutcheson and Early [Attorneys] to Bruce re legal business 1921 (Box 10)
  - Arthur Johnson to Bruce re business matters 1916 (Box 10)
  - Fred Kabler to Bruce re surveying 1917 (Box 10)
  - J. E. Peterson to Bruce re sale of lands 1917-1918 (Box 10)
  - Piedmont Lumber Co. to Bruce 1909-1910 (Box 10)
  - Stephen Randolph to Bruce re business matters 1926 (Box 10)
  - Venable and Ford Co. to Bruce re sale of property 1915-1916 (Box 10)
  - N. L. Williamson to Bruce re land sales 1922-1925 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, A - Z 20th century (Box 10)
  - Accounts and Tax Receipts 1916-1925 (Box 10)
  - Deeds, Indentures, Lease of Sale Agreements 1912-1918 (Box 10)
  - Sale notices 1925-1926 (Box 10)
  - Plats and land surveys n.d. (Box 10)